Finding Aid for M. Rupert Cutler papers, 1933-1962 and 1969-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
M. Rupert Cutler papers 1933-1962, 1969-1977
Cutler, M. Rupert.
5 linear feet
0160 Aa 2
Environmentalist, conversational journalist, educator; files and other materials relating to his education and training and to his professional activities in Michigan, Arizona, and Virginia.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of M. Rupert Cutler (donor no. 9015 ) and came to the library in September 2000.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
M. Rupert Cutler, an environmentalist and conservation journalist, was born in Detroit, Michigan. He received his undergraduate degree in wildlife management from the University of Michigan and his master's and doctor of philosophy degrees from the Department of Resource Development of Michigan State University.
Following his graduation from the University of Michigan in 1955, Cutler was briefly employed as an instruction book writer for Argus Cameras in Ann Arbor, Michigan. In 1956, he moved to Arizona where he edited a weekly newspaper, the Winslow Mail. In 1957, he accepted the post of executive secretary of Wildlife Conservation Incorporated in Boston and in 1958 he was hired by the Virginia Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries to be associate editor of Virginia Wildlife, the Virginia Game Department's magazine. In 1961, Cutler was promoted to Chief, Education Division, Virginia Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries. During the years 1962-1969, Cutler was in Washington D.C. serving as editor of publications of the National Wildlife Federation and then as assistant executive director of The Wilderness Society. He was also senior vice president of the National Audubon Society, executive director of Population-Environment Balance, and president of Defenders of Wildlife.
In 1969, Cutler returned to Michigan to study for his doctorate at Michigan State University and to work as a Graduate Research Assistant in MSU's Department of Resource Development. With his degree, he became assistant professor of resource development and the state's extension specialist in natural resources policy. In 1977 he was appointed by President Jimmy Carter to serve as assistant secretary of agriculture for conservation, research, and education. From 1977 to 1980 he provided policy direction to the U.S. Forest Service, the Soil Conservation Service, and USDA's research, extension, and library agencies.
Since January of 1991, M. Rupert Cutler has resided in Roanoke, Virginia. From 1991 to February of 1997, he was the executive director of Virginia's Explore Park, a 1,000-acre outdoor living history museum and environmental education center on the Roanoke River in Roanoke and Bedford counties. In March of 1997, M. Rupert Cutler became the founding executive director of the Western Virginia Land Trust, a new, private, nonprofit association created to help preserve the natural, scenic, and cultural heritage of western Virginia on private land, using conservation easements.
The Cutler collection consists of personal papers and memorabilia documenting the life and career of M. Rupert Cutler as an educator and environmentalist. In addition to his publications, the collection includes some correspondence, personal memorabilia, educational materials, and collected materials relating to his career and the environmental movement. The files have been retained in the order received with the descriptions provided by the donor. As requested, the collection only includes material from the period of time when M. Rupert Cutler was in Michigan. Most of the materials from 1962 to 1969 were retained by the donor.
Subjects:
Cutler, M. Rupert.; Environmentalism--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Environmentalism--Virginia.; Conservation of natural resources--Virginia.; Michigan State University--Faculty.
- Early years 1933-1954
  - 1933-1948
    - Hospital statement from Plymouth Hospital for his delivery (Box 1)
    - Original birth certificate (Box 1)
    - Baby book of earliest photos, mother's comments (Box 1)
    - Public school report cards (Box 1)
    - Boy Scout records, medals (Box 1)
    - Business card of dance band played in during the 1940s (Box 1)
    - Baptismal and confirmation certificates (Box 1)
    - Graduation certificate from intermediate school, personal notes and letters by MRC and his mother, etc. (Box 1)
  - 1949-1950
    - Cass Tech HS yearbooks from 1949, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Cass Tech school paper with photos of track team taken by MRC (Box 1)
    - Souvenirs from 1950 Scout Jamboree at Valley Forge (Box 1)
  - 1951
    - Cass Tech report cards, yearbook (Box 1)
    - Heidelberg College souvenirs (Box 1)
    - Audubon Camp of Maine certificate (Box 1)
    - Detroit Audubon Society Bird Survey Committee report (Box 1)
  - 1952
    - Record of Heidelberg College activities (Box 1)
    - Summer employment with Forest Service, original writings (Box 1)
    - Bird observations (Box 1)
    - Heidelberg yearbook (Box 1)
  - Fall 1952
    - Record of Wayne University (Detroit) activities (Box 1)
    - Smoke chaser's map of Forest Service lookout district (Box 1)
    - Letters home from Idaho (Box 1)
    - 1952 Detroit Audubon Society Bird Survey Committee report (Box 1)
      (MRC saw first piping plover nest in Michigan)
  - 1953
    - Final records at Wayne State University (Box 1)
    - Records of summer spent working for the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service in Alaska (Box 1)
    - Maps of Alaska (Box 1)
    - Original writings while working in Katmai National Monument (Box 1)
    - Federal bird collecting permit (Box 1)
    - Heidelberg yearbook (Box 1)
  - 1953
    - Letters home from Alaska (Box 1)
    - Letters from Dr. Sutton and Dr. Gabrielson thanking MRC for bird study skins collected in Alaska (Box 1)
    - Job offer from FWS, Detroit area bird survey (Box 1)
  - 1954
    - First University of Michigan records (Box 1)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs scholarship award (Box 1)
    - Letter about bleeding ulcer at U of M hospital (Box 1)
    - Articles written for/printed in Michigan Daily and Michigan Journalist newspapers (Box 1)
    - Binder containing all of MRC's articles written in the Michigan Daily plus photos taken by MRC of high school sports, scenery (Box 1)
    - Binder containing term paper on Smokey Bear program history (Box 1)
      (Award received from U of M School of Natural Resources)
    - 1954 Michigan Forester yearbook of School of Natural Resources (Box 1)
      (MRC was associate editor)
    - 1955 Michigan Forester yearbook (Box 1)
      (MRC was editor)
  - 1955
    - University of Michigan records (Box 2)
    - Commencement program (Box 2)
    - Draft Board papers (Box 2)
    - Arrangements for trip to Europe with Al Weisz (Box 2)
    - Letters signed by Ernest Swift, Ira Gabrielson, Dick McCardle, others (Box 2)
    - Foresters Club papers (Box 2)
    - Articles in campus papers (Box 2)
    - Offer a job from the Virginia Department of Game and Inland Fisheries (Box 2)
  - 1955
    - Souvenirs of Summer 1955 trip to Europe with fellow University of Michigan forester Al Weisz, including day-by-day journal (Box 2)
  - 1956
    - Marriage to Gladys Rothenbecker on March 23, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Record of employment as instruction book writer at Argus Cameras, Ann Arbor (Box 2)
    - Samples of instruction books written (Box 2)
    - Record of employment as editor of The Winslow Mail newspaper, Winslow, AZ (Box 2)
    - 1956 University of Michigan Forester (Box 2)
    - Personal correspondence (Box 2)
  - 1957
    - Correspondence and souvenirs of MRC's life in Winslow, AZ, as editor of The Winslow Mail weekly newspaper (Box 2)
    - Copies of The Winslow Mail edited by MRC (Box 2)
    - Exchanges of correspondence leading to his acceptance of post of executive secretary of Wildlife Conservation Incorporated in Boston, MA (Box 2)
    - Letters from Quincy, MA (Box 2)
    - Op-ed article in Boston Globe, December 1, 1957 (Box 2)
  - 1958
    - Correspondence between MRC and GFC (Box 2)
    - Record of MRC being hired by Virginia Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries to be associate editor of Virginia Wildlife (Box 2)
    - Issues of Virginia Wildlife (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with national leaders in wildlife conservation (Box 2)
    - MRC's first article on the problem of pesticides harming wildlife (in Virginia Wildlife) (Box 2)
  - Bound volumes
    - All press releases and newsletters ("Conservation Currents") written by MRC for Wildlife Conservation Incorporated, Boston, MA 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - Virginia Wildlife magazine, entire years of 1958, 1961, 1962 (edited by MRC) (Box 2)
  - 1959
    - Personal correspondence (Box 2)
    - Samples of Virginia Wildlife (Box 2)
    - Game commission press releases (Box 2)
    - Record of MRC playing trombone in the Richmond Symphony Orchestra (Box 2)
  - 1960
    - Records of MRC attending Richmond Professional Institute (Box 2)
    - Virginia Wildlife issues (Box 2)
    - Newspaper articles (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Record of MRC winning national award from American Association for Conservation Information (Box 2)
  - 1961
    - Record of MRC being promoted to Chief, Education Division, Virginia Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries (Box 2)
    - Virginia Wildlife issues (Box 2)
    - Dedication of National Wildlife Federation building in DC (Box 2)
    - MRC's articles on the Gathright Dam controversy in the Commonwealth magazine (Box 2)
- Career activities 1969-1972
  (Cutler retained his files for the years 1962-1969 when Cutler was in Washington, D.C. with the National Wildlife Federation and The Wilderness Society)
  - 1969
    - Correspondence covering transition from resigning as Assistant Executive Director of The Wilderness Society, Washington, DC, to becoming a Graduate Research Assistant in the Department of Resource Development, Michigan State University (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with the dean of the School of Natural Resources, University of Michigan with regard to possible graduate work there (Box 3)
    - Decision to attend Michigan State University (Box 3)
    - Paperwork associated with MRC's consultant work for the U.S. Department of Transportation (Box 3)
    - 1969 Presidential Inauguration official program (Nixon) (Box 3)
  - 1970 Part 1
    - Correspondence related to Michigan State University Earth Day Teach-In (Box 3)
    - Michigan State University reports of standing (Box 3)
    - Notice of receipt of Michigan United Conservation Clubs-National Wildlife Federation fellowship (Box 3)
    - Michigan Earth Day newspaper coverage (Box 3)
    - Speeches on the environment made to Michigan groups (Box 3)
  - 1970 Part 2
    - Material published by the Michigan Student Environmental Confederation (Box 3)
    - Environmental Action Bulletin published by Michigan State University (Box 3)
    - Collection of newspaper editorial cartoons on the need to protect the environment (Box 3)
    - Speeches by Michigan Governor Milliken on the need to protect the environment (Box 3)
    - Newly passed federal Environmental Education Act (Box 3)
    - Obituary of MRC's friend, Dr. Alfred E. Weisz, 36, of Los Altos Hills, CA, on July 23, 1970 (Box 3)
  - 1970 Part 3
    - Letter drafted by MRC, signed by President Clifton Wharton, announcing Michigan State University Earth Day teach-in April 21-22, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Program for University of Michigan Earth Day March 10-14, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Personal correspondence with many national conservation leaders (Box 3)
    - MRC's election to the board of the Mackinac Chapter of the Sierra Club (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with Senator Hart on the Sylvania Recreation Area (Box 3)
  - 1971 Part 1
    - MRC's appointment by Department of Natural Resources Director Ralph MacMullen to the Governor's Advisory Board on Natural Areas (Box 3)
    - MRC's speech to the 12th Biennial Sierra Club Wilderness Conference, Washington, DC 9/25/1971 on Preserving Wilderness Through State Legislation (Box 3)
    - MRC's article on wilderness in Michigan Out of Doors (Box 3)
  - 1971 Part 2
    - Examples of "Michigan Earth Beat" published by the Michigan Student Environmental Confederation (Box 3)
    - Michigan Governor Milliken's Special Message on the Environment 2/4/1971 (Box 3)
    - Milliken's proclamation: Earth Week '71 (Box 3)
    - Environmental voting records of Michigan congressional delegation (Box 3)
  - 1971 Part 3
    - Commencement program, Michigan State University 1971 (Box 3)
      (MRC receives M.S. from Department of Resource Development)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs statement of the president on the death of Jim Rouman, etc. (Box 3)
    - Plan for the Future, MUCC (Box 3)
  - 1971 Part 4
    - Lansing newspaper coverage of hearing to make the Porcupine Mountains State Park a wilderness area (Box 3)
    - Executive Order creating Advisory Council for Natural Areas (Box 3)
    - Michigan State University transcript (Box 3)
    - MRC initiated in Honor Society of Phi Kappa Phi (Box 3)
    - Sylvania Visitor Center dedication booklet 6/26/1971 (Box 3)
    - Letter signed by Hubert Humphrey (Box 3)
    - Publication, "Michigan's Environment" by Michigan Student Environmental Confederation (Box 3)
  - Two books
    - Environmental Quality: Now or Never (MSU) edited by Charles L. San Clemente (Box 3)
      (includes chapter by MRC)
    - Action for Wilderness (Sierra Club) edited by Elizabeth R. Gillette (Box 3)
      (includes chapter by MRC on Michigan Wilderness and Natural Areas Act)
  - 1972
    - Newspaper coverage of George McGovern's campaign rally in Lansing/East Lansing (Box 3)
    - Copies of "Michigan Earth Beat" newspaper published by Michigan Student Environmental Confederation (Box 3)
    - MRC's speech to Society of American Foresters in Milwaukee 3/16/1972 (Box 3)
    - Copy of H.B.4881 the Michigan Wilderness and Natural Areas Act of 1972 (Box 3)
    - Governor Milliken's Special Message to the Legislature on Land Use and the Environment 2/10/1972 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines for Michigan environmental impact statements (Box 3)
    - Michigan Natural Areas Council policy of establishment of outdoor classrooms on school sites (Box 3)
    - "Governor Signs 4881" (wilderness bill) (Box 3)
    - DNR Director MacMullan's speech to Michigan Bear Hunters on how pleased the DNR is that wilderness is the theme of their convention (Box 3)
    - Michigan State University Commencement Program 1972 listing MRC as receiving Ph.D. from Department of Resource Development (Box 3)
    - Letter to MRC from Governor Milliken on land use control (Box 3)
    - Personal letters to MRC signed by many Congressmen including Muskie, Dingell, etc. (Box 3)
    - Letter to MRC from former supervisor of the Ottawa National Forest about local attitudes toward the Sylvania Recreation Area (Box 3)
  - Two books on the Pigeon River Country State Forest
    - Pigeon River Country -- The Big Wild by Gordon Charles (Box 3)
    - The Pigeon River Country by Dale Clarke Franz (Box 3)
- Career activities 1973-1975
  - 1973-1974
    - MRC's consultant paper for the U.S. Forest Service, "Improvement of Forest Service Environmental Impact Statements through Better Guidelines on Analysis" (Box 4)
    - MRC's article "Public Involvement in Government Decisions" in Alternatives, Autumn 1974 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper report of Al Kaline's 3,000th hit (Box 4)
    - MRC's paper "New Role for Government Information and Education Personnel" presented at 39th North American Wildlife and Natural Resources Conference, Denver April 1974 (Box 4)
    - Copies of the Michigan State University Cooperative Extension Service newsletter, "Report from the Committee on Land and Water," edited by MRC (Box 4)
    - MRC's speech to Michigan Association of Farm Managers and Rural Appraisers, "Political Forces Affecting Land Use Policy," 1/24/1974 (Box 4)
    - MRC's speech to Michigan Chapter Society of American Foresters, "Pressing Needs in Land Use Planning," 3/21/1974 (Box 4)
    - U of M School of Natural Resources newsletter on resignation of Dean McFadden (Box 4)
    - Announcement of the appointment of MRC to the Pigeon River Country Advisory Council (Box 4)
    - Course announcement of MRC's new course, RD 480, Section 3, "Environmental Policy Process" (Box 4)
    - Extension press release 3/12/1973: "Cutler named natural resources policy specialist" (Box 4)
    - Bay City Times of 3/2/1973 with photo and story of MRC's involvement in hearing on proposed nuclear power plant at Midland (Box 4)
    - "Final Report Summary: A Study of Litigation Related to Management of Forest Service and Its Effect on Policy Decisions," by Dr. M. Rupert Cutler (Ph.D. thesis) issued by the Division of Forest Economics, North Central Forest Experiment Station, U.S. Forest Service (Box 4)
    - MSU "Board Action" approving the appointment of MRC as assistant professor in the tenure system 2/16/1973 (Box 4)
    - Several speeches to Extension audiences by MRC on land use, e.g., "Opportunities for Citizens to Influence Land Use Policies" 10/9/1973 (Box 4)
    - Paper given at 35th Midwest Fish and Wildlife Conference, St. Louis 12/5/1973 "A Rationale for More Public Involvement in Agency Decisionmaking Based on a Study of Recent Litigation" (Box 4)
    - Conference proceedings "Options in Land Use Policy for Michigan," April 8-9, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Copy of H.B. 4244 1974: the Michigan Farmland and Open Space Preservation Act (Box 4)
  - Bound report
    - "Improvement of Forest Service Environmental Statements Through Better Guidelines on Analysis," April 1975 prepared for the Environmental Coordinator, Forest Service, USDA, by MRC (Box 4)
  - 1975
    - State of Michigan Guidelines for the Preparation and Review of Environmental Impact Statements Under Executive Order 1974-4, dated 11/20/1975 issued by Gov. Milliken (Box 4)
    - "Earth Beat" newsletter of Michigan Student Environmental Confederation (Box 4)
    - Announcement of MSU Natural Resources Days March 24-26, 1975 organized by MRC (Box 4)
    - "The Forest Flare" newsletter of the Michigan Forest Association with article by MRC on "Who's Doing What to Whom in Regard to Oil in Michigan's Pigeon River Country State Forest" (Box 4)
    - Copy of H.B. 5398 to create the Michigan Environmental Review Board (Box 4)
    - Set of syllabuses outlining all the environmental quality-related courses at MSU (Box 4)
    - MSU Board Action approving MRC for second probationary appointment as Assistant Professor 5/22/1975 (Box 4)
    - Letter to MRC re agreeing to speak at MSU Natural Resources Days for Oregon Governor Tom McCall (Box 4)
    - Newspapers on "worst flood (in Lansing) since 1947" (Box 4)
    - MRC's paper. "Environmental Impact Statements: The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly," given at 37th Midwest Fish and Wildlife Conference, Toronto 12/9/1975 (Box 4)
    - Conference proceedings, "Integrating Land Use Planning and Environmental Impact Analysis," chaired by MRC, MSU 04/17/1919-04/18/1919 75 (Box 4)
- Career activities 1976-1977
  - 1976
    - MRC's paper, "Forestry and the Pigeon River Country Controversy," given to the Wisconsin-Michigan Section, Society of American Foresters, Gaylord 8/19/1976 (Box 5)
    - Handwritten and signed note from Tom McCall of Oregon (Box 5)
    - Report on 59th District Legislative Conference Report including MRC's role as speaker on environmental protection (Box 5)
    - Issues of The North Woods Call conservation newspaper published in Charlevoix, MI (Box 5)
    - Paper on the Kirtland's Warbler, "Michigan's Bicentennial Bird" (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clip Detroit News, on appointment by governor of MRC to Michigan Environmental Review Board (Box 5)
    - Nomination of MRC to receive the John Hannah Award for Extension Program Excellence, from department chair Ray Vlasin (Box 5)
    - Annual report of Michigan Lung Association (Box 5)
      (MRC on board of trustees)
    - Letter from Doug Scott, Sierra Club, to Kathy Fletcher of Carter staff recommending MRC for appointment as assistant secretary of agriculture, and similar letters, including letters from Sig Olson, Ely, MN (Box 5)
    - Letters to MRC from Clif Merritt and Alfreda Winnings on internal workings of The Wilderness Society (Box 5)
    - Letter from Henry H. Webster, Chief, Forestry Division, Michigan Department of Natural Resources, supporting MRC for assistant secretary of agriculture (Box 5)
    - Verbatim court testimony of MRC in Pigeon River Country State Forest oil development litigation (Box 5)
    - Law review article on "State Management of the Environment, Part 1, An Evaluation of the Michigan Experience" (Box 5)
    - Journal of Urban Law article on Michigan's Environmental Protection Act (Box 5)
    - MRC's role in Coastal Zone Management program in MI (Box 5)
    - MRC's paper, "Land Use: What is it, is it desirable?--State of Michigan Viewpoint," given to Xi Sigma Pi National Honor Forestry Society, Houghton 4/30/1976 (Box 5)
    - Letter from Se. Hart's office thanking MRC for help on Isle Royale wilderness legislation (Box 5)
    - MSU Extension press release, "Former Oregon Governor and Buffalo Featured at Natural Resources Banquet" (Box 5)
    - Copy of the National Forest Management Act of 1976 (Box 5)
    - M.S. thesis on House Interior Committee by Todd Bacon, MRC's advisee, with letter to him expressing appreciation (Box 5)
  - Documents:
    - (1) conference proceedings, "Options in Land Use Policy for Michigan," MSU April 8-9, 1974 (Box 5)
    - (2) conference proceedings, "Integrating Land Use Planning & Environmental Impact Analysis," MSU April 17-18, 1975 (Box 5)
    - (3) M.S. thesis, "State Regulation of Dam Construction and Operation in Michigan: A Problem Analysis," by Clifford H. Heckathorn (MRC's advisee) (Box 5)
    - (4) "Sowing the Seed: Early Oklahoma," annual report of the Ag. Experiment Station, OSU (Box 5)
  - 1977
    - Until nominated Assistant Secretary of Agriculture Includes MSU first Natural Resources Days program (Box 5)
    - North Woods Call editorial supportive of MRC's appointment as assist. Sec., USDA 3/9/1977 (Box 5)
    - Lletter to MRC from Ned Caveney, DNR forester in charge of Pigeon River Country State Forest, on MRC's resignation from PRC Advisory Council (Box 5)
    - Article in Iron River Reporter on MRC speech to extension audience 1/19/1977 "Cutler explains government influence process" (Box 5)
    - Letters recommending MRC for assistant secretary of agriculture (Box 5)
    - Letter from Governor William G. Milliken congratulating MRC on USDA appointment and accepting his resignation from the Michigan Environmental Review Board (Box 5)
    - MSU Department of Park and Recreation Resources newsletter: "Cutler joins Carter administration" (Box 5)
    - Michigan State University Faculty and Staff Directory 1976 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous additions (Box 5)
Related Material
The Jimmy Carter Presidential Library has an extensive collection of Cutler papers from the period when he served in the US Department of Agriculture.